Okay, so let me dive into some
administrative
points first. So again, recall that
assignment 1 is due next Wednesday.
You have about 150 hours left,
and I use hours because there's a more
imminent sense of doom and remember that
a third of those hours you'll be
unconscious, so you don't have that much
time. It's really running out. And you
know you might think that you have
late days and so on but these assignments just get
harder over time so you want to save
those and so on, so start now. Let's see. So
there's no office hours or anything like
that on Monday. I'll hold make up office
hours on Wednesday because I want you
guys to be able to talk to me about the
especially projects and so on, so I'll be
moving my office hours from Monday to
Wednesday. Usually I had my office hours
at 6PM. Instead I'll have them at 5PM
and usually it's in Gates 260 but now
it'll be in Gates 259, so minus 1 on both and yeah
and also to note, when you're going to be
studying for midterm that's coming up in
a few weeks
make sure you go through the lecture
notes as well which are really part of
this class and I kind of pick and choose
some of the things that I think are most
valuable to present in a lecture but
there's quite a bit of, you know, more material
to be aware of that might pop up in the
midterm, even though I'm covering some of
the most important stuff usually in the lecture,
so do read through those lecture
notes. They're complimentary to the lectures.
And so the material for the midterm will be
drawn from both the lectures and the notes. Okay.
So having said all that, we're going to
dive into the material. So where we are
right now, just as a reminder, we have
the score function, we looked at several
loss functions such as the SVM loss
function last time, and we look at the
full loss that you achieve for any
particular set of weights on, over your
training data, and this loss is made up of
two components. There's a data loss and
a regularization loss, right. And really what we want to do
is we want to derive out the gradient
expression of the loss function with respect to the
weights and we want to do this so that
we can actually perform the optimization
process. And in the optimization process we're doing
gradient descent, where we iterate evaluating
the gradient on your weights, doing a
parameter update and just repeating this
over and over again, so that we're
converging to
the low points of that loss function and
when we arrive at a low loss, that's
equivalent to making good predictions
over our training data in terms of the
scores that come out. Now we also saw
that are two kinds of ways to evaluate the
gradient. There's a numerical gradient
and this is very easy to write but it's
extremely slow to evaluate, and there's
analytic gradient, which is, which you
obtain by using calculus and we'll be
going into that in this lecture quite a
bit more and so it's fast, exact, which is
great, but it's not, you can get it wrong
sometimes, and so we always what we call
gradient check, where we write all
the expressions to compute the analytic
gradients, and then we double check its
correctness with numerical gradient and
so I'm not sure if you're going to see
that, you're going to see that definitely the
assignments. Okay, so, now you might be
tempted to, when you see this setup, we
just want to derive the gradient of the
loss function with respect to the weights. You
might be tempted to just, you know, right
out the full loss and just start to take
the gradients as you see your calculus
class, but the point I'd like to make is that you
should think much more of this in terms
of computational graphs, instead of just
taking, thinking of one giant expression
that you're going to derive with
pen and paper the expression for the
gradient and the reason for that
so here we are thinking about these
values flow, flowing through a
computational graph where you have these
operations along circles and they're
basically little function pieces that
transform your inputs all the way to the
loss function at the end, so we start off
with our data and our parameters as
inputs. They feed through this
computational graph, which is just all
these series of functions along the way,
and at the end, we get a single number
which is the loss. And the reason that
I'd like you to think about it this way is
that, these expressions right now look
very small and you might be able to
derive these gradients, but these
expressions are, in computational graphs, are
about to get very big and, so for example,
convolutional neural networks will have
hundreds maybe or dozens of operations,
so we'll have all these images
flowing through like pretty big computational
graph to get our loss and so it becomes
impractical to just write out these
expressions, and convolutional networks are
not even the worst of it. Once you
actually start to, for example, do
something called a Neural Turing Machine,
which is a paper from DeepMind, where
this is basically differentiable
Turing machine
so the whole thing is differentiable, the
whole procedure that the computer is
performing on a tape is made smooth
and is differentiable computer basically
and the computational graph of this is huge,
and not only is this, this is not it
because what you end up doing and we're
going to recurrent neural networks in a
bit, but what you end up doing is you end
up unrolling this graph, so think about
this graph copied many hundreds of time
steps and so you end up with this giant
monster of hundreds of thousands of
nodes and little computational units and
so it's impossible to write out, you know,
here's the loss for the Neural Turing
Machine. It's just impossible, it would
take like billions of pages, and so we
have to think about this more in terms
of data structures of little functions
transforming intermediate variables to
guess the loss at the very end. Okay. So we're going
to be looking specifically at
computational graphs and how we can derive
the gradient on the inputs with respect
to the loss function at the very end. Okay.
So let's start off simple and concrete. So let's
consider a very small computational graph where
we have scalars as inputs to this graph, x, y and
z, and they take on these specific values
in this example of -2, 5 and -4,
and we have this very small graph
or circuit, you'll hear me refer to these
interchangeably either as a graph or
a circuit, so we have this graph that at
the end gives us this output -12.
Okay. So here what I've done is I've
already pre-filled what we'll call the
forward pass of this graph, where I set
the inputs and then I compute the outputs
And now what we'd like to do is, we'd like to
derive the gradients of the expression on
the inputs, and, so what we'll do now, is,
I'll introduced this intermediate variable
q after the plus gate, so there's a plus gate
and times gate, as I'll refer to them, and
this plus gate is computing this output
q, and so q is this intermediate as
a result of x plus y, and then f is a
multiplication of q and z. And what I've written
out here is, basically, what we want is the
gradients, the derivatives, df/dx, df/dy,
df/dz. And I've written out
the intermediate, these little gradients
for every one of these two expressions
separately, so now we've performed forward
pass going from left to right, and what
we'll do now is we'll derive the backward
pass, we'll go from the back
to the front, computing gradients of all
the intermediates in our circuit until
at the very end, we're going to build up to
get the gradients on the inputs, and so we
start off at the very right and, as a
base case sort of this recursive
procedure, we're considering the gradient
of f with respective to f, so this is just the
identity function, so what is the
derivative of it,
identity mapping?
What is the gradient of df by df? It's one, right?
So the identity has a gradient of one.
So that's our base case. We start off
with a one, and now we're going to go
backwards through this graph. So, we want
the gradient of f with respect to z.
So what is that in this computational graph?
Okay, it's q, so we have that written out right
here and what is q in this particular
example? It's 3, right? So the gradient
on z, according to this will, become
just 3. So I'm going to be writing the gradients
under the lines in red and the values
are in green above the lines. So with the
gradient on the, in the front is 1, and
now the gradient on z is 3, and what red 3 is telling
you really intuitively, keep in mind the
interpretation of a gradient, is what
that's saying is that the influence of
z on the final value is positive and
with, sort of a force of 3. So if I
increment z by a small amount h
then the output of the circuit will
react by increasing, because it's a
positive 3, will increase by 3h, so
small change will result in a positive
change in the output. Now the
gradient on q in this case will be
So df/dq is z. What is z? -4. Okay?
So we get a gradient of -4 on that path
of the circuit, and what that's saying is
that if q were to increase, then the output
of the circuit will decrease, okay, by, if
you increase by h, the output of the circuit
will decrease by 4h. That's the
slope, is -4. Okay, now we're going
to continue this recursive process through this
plus gate and this is where things get
slightly interesting
I suppose. So we'd like to compute the
gradient on f on y with respect to y
and so the gradient on y in
this particular graph will become
Let's just guess and then we'll
see how this gets derived properly.
So I hear some murmurs of the right answer.
It will be -4. So let's see how.
So there are many ways to derive it at this point
because the expression is very small and you can
kind of, glance at it, but the way I'd like to
think about this is by applying chain rule, okay.
So the chain rule says that if you would
like to derive the gradient of f on y
then it's equal to df/dq times
dq/dy, right? And so we've
computed both of those expressions, in
particular dq/dy, we know, is
-4, so that's the effect of the
influence of q on f, is df/dq, which is
-4, and now we know the local,
we'd like to know the local influence
of y on q, and that local influence
of y on q is 1, because that's the local
as I'll refer to as the local derivative of y
for the plus gate, and so the chain rule
tells us that the correct thing to do to
chain these two gradients, the local
gradient of y on q, and the,
kind of global gradient of q on the
output of the circuit, is to multiply
them. So we'll get -4 times 1
And so, this is kind of the, the crux of how
backpropagation works. This is a very
important to understand here that, we have
these two pieces that we keep
multiplying through when we perform the chain rule.
We have q computed x + y, and
the derivative x and y, with respect to that
single expression is 1 and 1. So keep
in mind the interpretation of the gradient.
What that's saying is that x and y have a
positive influence on q, with a slope
of 1. So increasing x by h
will increase q by h, and what we'd eventually
like is, we'd like the influence of y
on the final output of the circuit, And so
the way this end up working is, you take
the influence of y on q, and we know
the influence of q on the final loss
which is what we are recursively
computing here through this graph, and
the correct thing to do is to multiply
them, so we end up with -4 times 1
gets you -4. And so the way this
works out is, basically what this is
saying is that the influence of y on
the final output of the circuit is -4
so increasing y should decrease the
output of the circuit by -4 times the
little change that you've made. And the way
that end up working out is y has a
positive influence on q, so increasing
y, slightly increases q
which slightly decreases the output of the circuit,
okay? So chain rule is kind of giving us this
correspondence. Go ahead.
(Student is asking question)
Yeap, thank you. So we're going to get into this.
You'll see many, basically this entire class
is about this, so you'll see many
many instantiations of this and
I'll drill this into you by the end of this
class and you'll understand it. You will not
have any symbolic expressions anywhere
once we compute this, once we're actually
implementing this and you'll see
implementations of it later in this.
It will always be just be vectors and numbers.
Raw vectors, numbers. Okay, and looking at x, we
have a very similar thing that happens.
We want df/dx. That's our final objective,
but, and we have to combine it.
We know what the x's, what is x's influence on q
and what is q's influence
on the end of the circuit, and so that
ends up being the chain rule, so you take
-4 times 1 and gives you -4, okay?
So the way this works, to generalize a
bit from this example and the way to think
about it is as follows. You are a gate
embedded in a circuit and this is a very
large computational graph or circuit and
you receive some inputs, some
particular numbers x and y come in
and you perform some operation f on them and
compute some output z. And now this
value of z goes into computational graph and
something happens to it but you're just
a gate hanging out in a circuit and
you're not sure what happens, but by the
end of the circuit the loss gets computed, okay? And
that's the forward pass and then we're
proceeding recursively in the reverse
order backwards, but before that actually,
before I get to that part, right away when I get
x and y, the thing I'd like to point out that
during the forward pass, if you're this
gate and you get to your values x and y
you compute your output z, and there's another
thing you can compute right away and
that is the local gradients on x and y.
So I can compute those right away
because I'm just a gate and I know what
I'm performing, like say addition or
multiplication, so I know the influence that
x and y have on my output value, so I can
compute those guys right away, okay? But then
what happens
near the end, so the loss gets computed
and now we're going backwards, I'll eventually learn
about what is my influence on
the final output of the circuit, the loss.
So I'll learn what is dL/dz in there.
The gradient will flow into me and what I
have to do is I have to chain that
gradient through this recursive case, so
I have to make sure to chain the
gradient through my operation that I performed
and it turns out that the correct thing
to do here by chain rule, really what it's
saying, is that the correct thing to do is to
multiply your local gradient with that
gradient and that actually gives you the
dL/dx that gives you the
influence of x on the final output of
the circuit. So really, chain rule is just
this added multiplication. where we take our,
what I'll call, global gradient of this
gate on the output, and we chain it
through the local gradient, and the same
thing goes for y. So it's just a
multiplication of that guy, that gradient
by your local gradient if you're a gate.
And then remember that these x's and y's
they are coming from different gates, right?
So you end up with recursing
this process through the entire computational
circuit, and so these gates
just basically communicate to each other
the influence on the final loss, so they
tell each other, okay if this is a positive
gradient that means you're positively
influencing the loss, if it's a negative
gradient you're negatively
influencing the loss, and these just get all
multiplied through the circuit by these
local gradients and you end up with, and
this process is called backpropagation.
It's a way of computing through a
recursive application of chain rule
through computational graph, the influence
of every single intermediate value in
that graph on the final loss function.
So we'll see many examples of this
throughout the lecture. I'll go into a
specific example that is a slightly
larger and we'll work through it in detail.
But I don't know if there are any questions at
this point that anyone would like to ask.
Go ahead.
What happens if z is used by two other nodes?
If z is used by multiple nodes, I'm going to come back to that.
You add the gradients. The gradient, the
correct thing to do is you add them.
So if z is being influenced in multiple places
in the circuit, the backward flows will add.
I will come back to that point. Go ahead.
(Student is asking question)
Yeap. So I think, I would've repeated your question,
but you're jumping ahead like 100 slides.
So we're going to get the all of those
issues and we're going to see, you're
going to get what we call vanishing
gradient problems and so on.
We'll see. Okay, let's go through another
example to make this more concrete.
So here we have another circuit. It happens
to be computing a little two-dimensional
sigmoid neuron, but for now don't worry about
that interpretation. Just think of this
as, that's an expression so one-over-
one-plus-e-to-the-whatever, so the number of
inputs here is five, and we're computing that function
and we have a single output over there, okay?
And I've translated that mathematical expression
into this computational graph form, so
we have to recursively from inside out
compute this expression so we first do
all the little w times x's, and then
we add them all up and then we take a
negative of it and then we exponentiate
that and then we add one and then we
finally divide and we get the result of
the expression. And so what we're going to do
now is we're going to backpropagate
through this expression. We're going to
compute what the influence of every
single input value is on the output of
this expression, what is the gradient here.
Yeap, go ahead.
(Student is asking question)
So for now, so you're concerned about the
interpretation of plus may be in these circles.
For now, let's just assume that this plus is a binary
plus. It's a binary plus gate, and we have there
plus one gate. I'm making up these gates on
the spot, and we'll see that what is a
gate or is not a gate is kind of up to
you. I'll come back to this point in a bit.
So for now, I just like, we have several more
gates that we're using throughout, and so
I'd just like to write out as we go
through this example several of these
derivatives. So we have exponentiation and
we know for every little local gate what these
local gradients are, right? So we can derive
that using calculus. So e^x derivative is e^x and
so on. So these are all the operations
and also addition and multiplication
which I'm assuming that you have
memorized in terms of what the gradients
look like. So we're going to start
off at the end of the circuit and I've
already filled in a 1.00
in the back because that's how we always
start this recursion with a 1.0
right, since that's the gradient
on the identity function. Now we're going
to backpropagate through this 1/x
operation, okay? So the derivative of 1/x
the local gradient is -1/(x^2),
so that 1/x gate
during the forward pass received
input 1.37 and right away that 1/x gate
could have computed what the
local gradient was. The local gradient was
-1/(x^2) and now during backpropagation,
it has to, by chain rule,
multiply that local gradient by the
gradient of it on the final output of the circuit
which is easy because it happens
to be at the end. So what ends up being the
expression for the backpropagated
gradient here, from the 1/x gate?
The chain rule always has two pieces: local
gradient times the gradient from the top
or from above.
(Student is answering)
Um, yeah. Okay. Yeah, so that's correct.
So we get -1/x^2, which is the gradient df/dx.
So that is the local gradient.
-1/3.7^2 and then multiplied by 1.0 which is
the gradient from above, which is really just 1
because we've just started, and I'm applying
chain rule right away here and the output is
-0.53. So that's the gradient on
that piece of the wire, where this value
was flowing, okay. So it has a negative
effect on the output. And you might expect
that right, because if you were to
increase this value and then it goes
through a gate of 1/x, then if you
increase this, 1/x get smaller, so
that's why you're seeing a negative
gradient, right. So we're going to continue
backpropagation here. The next gate
in the circuit, it's adding a constant of 1,
so the local gradient, if you look at
adding a constant to a value, the
gradient on x is just 1, right,
from basic calculus. And so the chained
gradient here that we continue along the wire
will be...
(Student is answering)
We have a local gradient, which is
1, times the gradient from above the
gate, which it has just learned is -0.53, okay?
So -0.53 continues along the
wire unchanged. And intuitively that
makes sense right, because this value
floats and it has some influence on the
final circuit and now, if you're
adding 1, then its influence, its rate
of change, its slope towards the final
value doesn't change. If you increase
this by some amount, the effect at the
end will be the same, because the rate of
change doesn't change through the +1 gate.
It's just a constant offset, okay? We continue
derivation here. So the gradient of e^x is
e^x, so to continue backpropagation
we're going to perform,
so this gate saw input of -1.
It right away could have computed its
local gradient, and now it knows that the
gradient from above is -0.53.
So to continue backpropagation
here and apply chain rule, we would receive...
(Student is answering)
Okay, so these are most of
the rhetorical questions so I'm
not sure, but yeah, basically
e^(-1) which is the e^x,
the x input to this exp gate times the chain rule,
right, so the gradient from above is -0.53
so we keep multiplying that on. So what
is the effect on me and what do I have an
effect on the final end of the circuit,
those are being always multiplied. So we
get -0.2 at this point. So now we
have a *(-1) gate. So what
ends up happening, what happens to the
gradient when you do a times -1 in the
computational graph?
It flips around, right? Because we have
basically, a constant multiply of input
which happened to be a constant of
-1, so 1 * -1
gave us -1 in the forward pass,
and so now we have to
multiply by a, that's the local gradient,
times the gradient from above which is -0.2
so we end up with just +0.2 now.
So now we're continuing backpropagation
We're backpropagating '+' and this '+' operation
has multiple inputs here, the gradient,
the local gradient for the plus gate is 1
and 1, so what ends up happening to,
what gradients flow along the output wires?
So the plus gate has a local gradient on all
of its inputs always will be just one, right, because
if you just have a function, you know,
x+y, then for that function
the gradient on either x or y is just one
and so what you end up getting is just
1 * 0.2. And so, in fact for a
plus gate, always you see the same fact
where the local gradient of all of its
inputs is 1, and so whatever gradient it
gets from above, it just always
distributes gradient equally to all of
its inputs, because in the chain rule,
they'll get multiplied and when you multiply by 1
something remains unchanged. So a '+'
gate, it's kind of like a gradient
distributor, where if something flows in
from the top, it will just spread out all
the gradients equally to all of its
children. And so we've already received
one of the inputs is gradient 0.2 here
on the very final output of the circuit
and so this influence has been computed
through a series of applications of
chain rule along the way. There was another
plus gate that I've skipped over, and so this
0.2 kind of distributes to both
0.2 0.2 equally so we've already done a
plus gate, and there's a multiply gate there,
and so now we're going to backpropagate
through that multiply operation.
And so the local grad, so the,
so what will be the gradients for w0 and x0?
What will be the gradient for w0, specifically?
(Student is answering)
Did someone say 0? 0 will be wrong. It will be,
so the gradient w1 will be, w0 sorry, will be
-1 * 0.2. Good. And the gradient on x0 will
be, there is a bug, by the way, in the slide
that I just noticed like few minutes
before I actually created the class.
Created the, started the class. So you see
0.39 there it should be 0.4. It's
because of a bug in the visualization
because I'm truncating at 2-decimal
digits, but anyways, basically that should be
0.4 because the way you get that
is 2 * 0.2 gives you 0.4
just like I've written out over there.
So that's what the output should be there.
Okay, so we've backpropagated this
circuit here and we've backpropagated through
this expression and so you might imagine in
our actual downstream applications,
we'll have data and all the parameters as inputs
the loss function is at the top at the
end, so we'll do forward pass to evaluate
the loss function and then we'll backpropagate
through every piece of
computation we've done along the way, and
we'll backpropagate through every gate to
get our inputs, and backpropagate just
means apply chain rule many many times
and we'll see how that is implemented in a bit.
Sorry, did you have a question?
(Student is asking question)
Oh yes, so I'm going to skip
that because it's the same.
So I'm going to skip the other times gate.
Any other questions at this point?
(Student is asking question)
That's right. so the costs of forward and
backward propagation are roughly equal.
(Student is asking question)
Well, it should be, it almost always ends
up being basically equal when you look
at timings, usually the backward pass is slightly
slower, but yeah.
Okay, so let's see, one thing I
wanted to point out, before we move on, is that
the setting of these gates, like these
gates are arbitrary, so one thing I could
have done, for example, is, some of you
may know this, I can collapse these gates
into one gate if I wanted to. For example,
There is something called the sigmoid function
which has that particular form, so a sigma of x
which is the sigmoid function
computes 1/(1+e^(-x))
and so I could have rewritten that
expression and I could have collapsed all of
those gates that made up the sigmoid
gate into a single sigmoid gate. And so there's a
sigmoid gate here, and I could have done
that in a single go, sort of, and what I
would have had to do, if I wanted to have
that gate, is I need to compute an
expression for how this, so what is the
local gradient for the sigmoid gate
basically? So what is the gradient on the
sigmoid gate on its input and I have to go
through some math which I'm not going to
go into detail but you end up with that
expression over there.
It ends up being (1-sigmoid(x)) * sigmoid(x).
That's the local gradient and that
allows me to now, put this piece into a
computational graph, because once I know
how to compute the local gradient
everything else is defined just through
chain rule and multiply everything
together. So we can backpropagate
through this sigmoid gate now, and the way
that would look like is, the input to the
sigmoid gate was 1.0, that's what
went into the sigmoid gate, and 0.73 went out.
So 0.73 is sigma of x, okay? And now we want
the local gradient which is, as we've seen
from the math that I performed there
(1 - sigma(x)) * sigma(x)
so you get, sigma(x) is 0.73, multiplying (1 - 0.73)
that's the local gradient and then times,
we happen to be at the end
of the circuit, so times 1.0,
which I'm not even writing.
So we end up with 0.2. And of course we
get the same answer
0.2, as we received before, 0.2,
because calculus works, but basically we
could have broken up
this expression down and
did one piece at a time or we could just
have a single sigmoid gate and that's
kind of up to us at what level of hierarchy
do we break these expressions
and so you'd like to
intuitively, cluster these expressions
into single gates if it's very efficient
or easy to derive the local gradients
because then those become your pieces.
(Student is asking question)
Yes. So the question is, do libraries typically
do that? Do they worry about, you know
what's easy to or convenient to
compute and the answer is yeah, I would say so,
So if you noticed that there are some
piece of operation you'd like to do over
and over again, and it has a very simple
local gradient, then that's something very
appealing to actually create a single
unit out of, and we'll see some of those
examples actually int a bit I think.
Okay, I'd like to also point out that once you,
the reason I like to think about these
computational graphs, is it really helps
your intuition to think about how gradients
flow in a neural network. It's not just,
you don't want this to be a black
box to you, you want to understand
intuitively how this happens, and you
start to develop after a while of
looking at computational graphs intuitions
about how these gradients flow, and this
by the way, helps you debug some issues like,
say, we'll go to vanishing gradient problem
it's much easier to understand exactly
what's going wrong in your optimization
if you understand how gradients flow
in networks. It will help you debug these
networks much more efficiently. And so
some intuitions for example, we already
saw the add gate. It has a local
gradient of 1 to all of its inputs, so
it's just a gradient distributor. That's
like a nice way to think about it
whenever you have a plus operation
anywhere in your score function or your
ConvNet or anywhere else. It just
distributes gradients equally. The max gate is
instead, a gradient router, and the way this
works is, if you look at the expression
like, we have. Great, these markers don't
work. So if you have a very simple binary
expression of max(x, y), so this is a gate.
Then, the gradient on x and y, if you
think about it, the gradient on the larger
one of your inputs, whichever one was larger
the gradient on that guy is one and all this,
and the smaller one has a gradient of 0.
And intuitively, that's because if one
of these was smaller, then wiggling it has no
effect on the output because the other
guy is larger and that's what ends up
propagating through the gate.
So you end up with a gradient of 1 on the
larger one of the inputs, and so that's
why max gate is a gradient router. If I'm
a max gate and I have received several
inputs, one of them was the largest of
all of them and that's the value that I
propagated through the circuit.
At backpropagation time, I'm just going to
receive my gradient from above and I'm
going to route it to whoever was my
largest input. So it's a gradient router.
And the multiply gate is a gradient switcher.
Actually I don't think that's a very good
way to look at it, but I'm referring to
the fact that it's not actually
nevermind about that part.
Go ahead.
(Student is asking question)
So your question is what happens if the two
inputs are equal when
you go through max gate.
Yeah, what happens?
(Student is answering)
Yeah, you pick one. Yeah.
Yeah, I don't think it's
correct to distributed to all of them. I
think you'd have to pick one.
But that basically never
happens in actual practice.
Okay, so max gradient here, I actually
have an example. So z, here, was larger
than w, so only z has an influence on
the output of this max gate, right?
So when 2 flows into the max gate
it gets routed to z, and w gets a 0 gradient
because its effect on the circuit is
nothing. There is 0, because when you
change it, it doesn't matter when you change
it, because z is the larger value
going through the computational graph.
I have another note that is related to
backpropagation which we already
addressed through a question. I just wanted
to briefly point out with a terribly
bad looking figure that if you have
these circuits and sometimes you have a
value that branches out into a circuit
and is used in multiple parts of the
circuit, the correct thing to do by
multivariate chain rule, is to actually
add up the contributions at the operation.
So gradients add when they backpropagate
backwards through the circuit. If they
ever flow, they add up in these backward flow
All right. We're going to go into
implementation very soon. I'll just take some
more questions.
(Student is asking question)
Thank you for the question. The question
is, is there ever, like a loop in these
graphs. There will never be loops, so there
are never any loops. You might think that
if you use a recurrent neural network,
that there are loops in there
but there are actually no loops because what
we'll do is we'll take a recurrent neural
network and we will unfold it through time
steps and this will all become, there
will never be a loop in the unfolded graph where
we've copied pasted that small recurrent net piece
over time.
You'll see that more when we actually
get into it but these are always DAGs
There are no loops.
Okay, awesome.
So let's look at the implementation of how this
is actually implemented in practice and
I think it will help make this more
concrete as well. So we always have these
graphs, computational graphs.
These are the best way to
think about structuring neural networks.
And so what we end up with is, all these
gates that we're going to see a bit, but
on top of the gates, there something's that
needs to maintain connectivity structure
of this entire graph, what gates are
connected to each other. And so usually
that's handled by a graph or a net object,
usually a net, and the net object has these
two main pieces, which is the forward
and the backward piece. And this is just pseudo
code, so this won't run, but basically,
roughly the idea is that in the forward pass
we're iterating over all the gates in the circuit
that, and they're sorted in topological
order. What that means is that all the
inputs must come to every node before
the output can be consumed. So these are just
ordered from left to right and we're just
forwarding, we're calling a forward on every
single gate along the way so we iterate
over that graph and we just go forward in
every single piece and this net object will
just make sure that happens in the
proper connectivity pattern. In backward
pass, we're going in the exact reversed
order and we're calling backward on
every single gate and these gates will
end up communicating gradients through each
other and they all get chained up and
computing the analytic gradient at the back.
So really a net object is a very thin
wrapper around all these gates, or as we
will see they're called layers, layers or
gates. I'm going to use those interchangeably
and they're just very thin wrappers
around connectivity structure of these
gates and calling a forward and backward
function on them. And then let's look at
a specific example of one of the gates
and how this might be implemented.
And this is not just a pseudo code.
This is actually more like correct
implementation. Something like this might run
at the end. So let's consider a multiply
gate and how it could be implemented.
A multiply gate, in this case, is just a
binary multiply, so it receives two inputs
x and y. It computes their multiplication,
z = x * y and it returns z.
And all these gates must basically satisfied this
API of a forward call and a backward call. How
do you behave in a forward pass, and how
do you behave in a backward pass. And
in a forward pass, we just compute whatever.
In a backward pass, we eventually end up
learning about what is our gradient on
the final loss. So dL/dz is what
we learn. That's represented in this
variable dz, and right now
everything here is scalars, so x, y, z are
numbers here. dz is also a number
telling the influence on the end of the circuit.
And what this gate is in charge
of in this backward pass is
performing the little piece of chain rule.
So what we have to compute is how do you
chain this gradient dz into your inputs x and y.
In other words, we have to compute
dx and dy and we have to
returned those in the backward pass, And then
the computational graph will make sure
that these get routed properly to all
the other gates. And if there are any
edges that add up, the computational graph
might add all those gradients together.
Okay, so how would we implement
the dx and dy? So for example, what is
dx in this case? What would it be equal to,
the implementation?
y * dz. Great. And, so y * dz.
Additional point to make here by the way,
note that I've added some lines in the forward
pass. We have to remember these values of
x and y, because we end up using them in the
backward pass, so I'm assigning them to a
'self.' because I need to remember
what x y are because I need access to
them in my backward pass. In general, in
backpropagation, when we build these,
when you actually do forward pass, every
single gate must remember the inputs in
any kind of intermediate calculations that it has
performed that it needs to do, that needs
access to in the backward pass. So basically
when we end up running these networks at
runtime, just always keep in mind that as
you're doing this forward pass, a huge
amount of stuff gets cached in your
memory, and that all has to stick around
because during backpropagation, you might
need access to some of those variables.
And so, your memory ends up ballooning up
during the forward pass, and then in backward pass,
it gets all consumed and we need all those
intermediates to actually compute the
proper backward pass. So that's...
(Student is asking question)
Yes, so if you don't, if you know you
don't want to do backward pass,
then you can get rid of
many of these things and you
don't have to compute, you don't need to cache
them. So you can save memory for sure.
But I don't think most implementations
actually worriy about that. I don't
think there's a lot of logic that deals with that.
Usually we end up remembering it anyway.
(Student is asking question)
I see. Yes, so I think if you're in the
embedded device for example, and you worry
really about your memory constraints, this is
something that you might take advantage
of. If you know that a neural network only
has to run in test time, then you might
want to make sure to go into the code to
make sure nothing gets cached in case
you want to do a backward pass.
Questions. Yes.
(Student is asking question)
You're saying if we remember the local gradients in
the forward pass, then we don't have to
remember the other intermediates?
I think that might only be the case in
some simple expressions like this one. I'm
not actually sure if that's true in general.
But I mean, you're in charge of, remember
whatever you need to, perform the
backward pass, and on a gate-by-gate basis.
You can remember whatever
you feel like. It has lower footprint and so on.
You can be clever with that. Okay, so just to give
you guy's example of what this looks like in
practice, we're going to look at specific
examples, say, in Torch. Torch is a deep
learning framework, which we might
go into a bit near the end of the class.
Some of you might end up using for
your projects. If you go into the Github repo
for Torch, and you'll look at,
basically, it's just a giant collection
of these layer objects and these are the
gates. Layers, gates, the same thing. So there's
all these layers. That's really what a
deep learning framework is. It's just a
whole bunch of layers and a very thin
computational graph thing that keeps track
of all the layer connectivity. And so really,
the image to have in mind is all these
things are your Lego blocks, and then we're
building up these computational graphs out of
your Lego blocks, out of the layers.
You're putting them together in various
ways depending on what you want to
achieve, so you end building all
kinds of stuff. So that's how you work
with neural networks. So every library is
just a whole set of layers that you
might want to compute, and every layer is
just implementing a small function piece, and
that function piece knows how to do a
forward and it knows how to do a backward.
So just to view the specific example, let's
look at the MulConstant layer in
Torch. The MulConstant layer performs
just a scaling by a scalar. So it takes
some tensor X. So this is not a scalar
but it's actually like an array of
numbers basically, because when we
actually work with these, we do a lot of
vectorized operation so we receive a tensor
which is really just a n-dimensional
array, and we scale it by a constant. And you
can see that this layer actually just has 40
lines. There's some initialization stuff.
This is Lua, by the way, if this is
looking some foreign to you, but there's
initialization, where you actually
pass in that a that you want to use as
your scaling, and then during the
forward pass which they call updateOutput
in a forward pass all they do is
they just multiply aX and return it. And
in the backward pass which they call
updateGradInput, there's an if statement
here but really when you look at these
three lines, they're most important. You can
see that all it's doing is it's copying into a
variable gradInput
which it needs to compute. That's your gradient
that you're passing up. The gradInput is,
you're copying gradOutput. gradOutput is
your gradient on final loss.
You're copying that over into gradInput
and you're multiplying by the scalar,
which is what you should be doing
because your local gradient is just a
and so you take the output you have, you
take the gradient from above and you just
scale it by a, which is what these three
lines are doing. And that's your gradInput
and that's what you return. So
that's one of the hundreds of layers
that are in Torch. We can also look
at examples in Caffe. Caffe is also a
deep learning framework specifically for
images that you might be working with. Again, if
you go into the layers directory in GitHub,
you just see all these layers. All of them implement
the forward backward API. So just to give
you an example, there's a sigmoid layer in Caffe.
So sigmoid layer takes a blob. So Caffe likes to
call these tensors blobs. So it takes a
blob. It's just an n-dimensional array of
numbers, and it passes it
elementwise through a sigmoid function. And so
it's computing in a forward pass a
sigmoid, which you can see there. Let me use my
pointer. Okay, so there, its calling, so a lot of
this stuff is just boilerplate, getting
pointers to all the data, and then we
have a bottom blob, and we're calling a
sigmoid function on the bottom and
that's just a sigmoid function right there.
So that's what we compute. And in the
backward pass, some boilerplate stuff, but
really what's important is we need to
compute the gradient times the chain
rule here, so that's what you see in this
line. That's where the magic happens
where we take the diff,
so they call the gradients diffs. And you
compute the bottom diff is the top diff
times this piece which is really the,
that's the local gradient, so this is
chain rule happening right here through
that multiplication. So, and that's it. So every
single layer just a forward backward API
and then you have a computational graph
on top or a net object that keeps track of all the
connectivity. Any questions about some of
these implementations and so on? Go ahead.
(Student is asking question)
Yes, thank you. So the question is, do we have to
go through forward and backward for every update.
The answer is yes, because when you
want to do update, you need the gradient,
and so you need to do forward
on your sample minibatch.
You do a forward. Right away you do a backward.
And now you have your analytic gradient.
And now I can do an update, where I take my
analytic gradient and I change my weights a tiny
bit in the direction, the negative direction
of your gradient. So forward computes
the loss, backward computes your gradient,
and then the update uses the gradient to
increment your weights a bit. So that's what keeps
happening in the loop. When you train a neural
network that's all that's happening. Forward,
backward, update. Forward, backward, update.
We'll see that in a bit. Go ahead.
(Student is asking question)
You're asking about a for-loop.
Oh, is there a for-loop here?
I didn't even notice. Okay.
Yeah, they have a for-loop. Yes, so you'd like
this to be vectorized and that actually...
Because this is C++, so I think they just do it.
Go for it.
Yeah, so this is a CPU implementation by
the way. I should mention that this is a
CPU implementation of a sigmoid layer.
There's a second file that implements the
sigmoid layer on GPU and that's CUDA code.
And so that's a separate file. It
would be sigmoid.cu or
something like that. I'm not showing you that.
Any questions? Okay, great. So one point I'd like to
make is, we'll be of course working with
vectors, so these things flowing along our
graphs are not just scalars. They're going
to be entire vectors. And so nothing
changes. The only thing that is different
now since these are vectors, x, y, and z are
vectors, is that this local gradient
which before used to be just a scalar,
now they're in general, for general
expressions, they're full Jacobian matrices.
And so Jacobian matrix is this
two-dimensional matrix and basically
tells you what is the influence of every
single element in x on every single
element of z,
and that's what Jacobian matrix
stores, and the gradient is the same
expression as before, but now, say here,
dz/dx is a vector and dL/dz is... sorry.
dL/dz is a vector and dz/dx is an
entire Jacobian matrix, so you end up with
an entire matrix-vector multiply to
actually chain the gradient backwards.
(Student is asking question)
No. So I'll come back to this point in a bit.
You never actually end up forming the full
Jacobian. You'll never actually do this
matrix multiply most of the time. This is
just a general way of looking at, you
know, arbitrary function, and I need to
keep track of this. And I think that
these two are actually out of order
because dz/dx is the Jacobian
which should be on the left side, so
I think that's a mistaken slide because
this should be a matrix-vector multiply.
So I'll show you why you don't actually
need to ever perform those Jacobians. So let's
work with a specific example that is
relatively common in neural networks.
Suppose we have this nonlinearity max(0, x)
So really what this operation
is doing is it's receiving a vector, say
4096 numbers, which is a typical thing
you might want to do.
4096 numbers, real value, come in
and you're computing an element-wise
thresholding at 0, so anything that is lower
than 0 gets clamped to 0, and that's your
function that you're computing. And so output
vector is of the same dimension. So
the question here I'd like to ask is
what is the size of the
Jacobian matrix for this layer?
4096 by 4096. In principle,
every single number in here could have
influenced every single number in there.
But that's not the case necessarily, right?
So the second question is, so this
is a huge matrix, 16 million numbers,
but why would you never form it?
What does the Jacobian actually look like?
(Student is asking question)
No, Jacobian will always be a matrix
because every one of these 4096
could have influenced every... It is, so the
Jacobian is still a giant 4096 by 4096
matrix, but has special structure, right?
And what is that special structure?
(Student is answering)
Yeah, so this Jacobian is huge.
So it's 4096 by 4096 matrix, but
there are only elements on the diagonal
because this is an element-wise operation,
and moreover, they're not just 1's, but
for whichever element that was less than 0,
it was clamped to 0, so some of these 1's
actually are zeros, in whichever elements
had a lower-than-zero value during the
forward pass. And so the Jacobian would
just be almost an identity matrix but
some of them are actually zero. So you
never actually would want to form the
full Jacobean because that's silly and
so you never actually want to carry out
this operation as a matrix vector
multiply, because of their special structure
that we want to take advantage of. And so
in particular, the gradient, the backward
pass for this operation is very very
easy because you just want to look at
all the dimensions where your input was
less than zero and you want to kill the
gradient in those dimensions. You want to
set the gradient to 0 in those dimensions.
So you take the grad output here, and
whichever numbers were less than zero,
just set them to 0. Set those gradients to 0
and then you continue backward pass.
So very simple operations in the
end in terms of efficiency.
(Student is asking question)
That's right.
So the question is, the commication between the
gates is always just vectors. That's right.
So this Jacobian, if you wanted to, you can form
that but that's internal to you inside the gate.
And you can use that to do backprop, but
what's going back to other gates, they
only care about the gradient vector.
(Student is asking question)
Yes, so the question is, unless
you end up having multiple outputs,
because then for each output,
we have to do this, so yeah.
So we'll never actually run into that case
because we almost always have a single
output, scalar value at the end
because we're interested in loss
functions. So we just have a single
number at the end that we're interested
in computing gradients with respect to. If we had
multiple outputs, then we have to keep
track of all of those as well
in parallel when we do the backpropagation.
But we just have scalar value loss
function so we don't have to worry about that.
Okay, makes sense? So I want
to also make the point that actually
4096 dimensions is not even crazy. Usually
we use minibatches, so say, minibatch of a
100 elements going through at the same
time, and then you end up with 100
4096-dimensional vectors that are all
coming in parallel, but all the examples
in the minibatch are processed independently of
each other in parallel, and so this Jacobian matrix
really ends up being 400 million, 400,000 by 400,000.
So huge so you never form these,
basically. And you take, you take care to
actually take advantage of the sparsity
structure in the Jacobian and you hand
code operations, so you don't actually write
fully generalized chain rule inside
any gate implementation. Okay cool. So I'd like
to point out that in your assignment, you'll be
writing SVMs and Softmax and so on, and I just kind
of would like to give you a hint on the design
of how you actually should approach this
problem. What you should do is just think
about it as a backpropagation, even if
you're doing this for linear classification
optimization. So roughly, your structure
should look something like this where...
again, stage your computation in units that
you know the local gradient of and then
do backprop when you actually evaluate these
gradients in your assignment. So in the
top, your code will look something like
this where we don't have any graph
structure because you're doing
everything inline. So no crazy edges
or anything like that that you have to do.
You will do that in the second assignment.
You'll actually come up with a graph
object and you'll implement your layers. But in
the first assignment, you're just doing it inline
just straight up vanilla setup. And so
compute your scores based on W and X.
Compute these margins which are max of 0
and the score differences, compute the
loss, and then do backprop. And in
particular, I would really advise you to
have this intermediate scores that you
create. It's a matrix. And then compute the
gradient on scores before you compute
the gradient on your weights. And so
chain, use chain rule here. Otherwise, you might
be tempted to try to just derive W, the
gradient on W equals, and then implement
that and that's an unhealthy way of
approaching the problem. So stage your
computation and do backprop through this
scores and that will help you out.
Okay. cool.
So, let's see. Summary so far.
Neural networks are hopelessly large,
so we end up in this
computational structures and these
intermediate nodes, forward backward API
for both the nodes and also for the
graph structure. And the graph structure is
usually a very thin wrapper around all these
layers and it handles all the
communication between them. And this
communication is always along like
vectors being passed around. In practice,
when we write these implementations, what
we're passing around are these
n-dimensional tensors. Really what that
means is just an n-dimensional array.
So like an numpy array. Those are what goes
between the gates, and then internally, every single
gate knows what to do in the forward and
the backward pass. Okay, so at this point, I'm
going to end with backpropagation and
I'm going to go into neural networks. So
any questions before we move on from
backprop? Go ahead.
(Student is asking a question)
The summation inside Li = blah?
Yes, there is a sum there.
So you want that to be vectorized operation that
you... Yeah so basically, the challenge in your
assignment almost is,
how do you make sure that you do all
this efficiently nicely with matrix vector operations
in numpy, so that's going to be some of the
brain teaser stuff that you guys are
going to have to do.
(Student is asking a question)
Yes, so it's up to you what you want your gates
to be like, and what you want them to be.
(Student is asking a question)
Yeah, I don't think you'd want to do that.
Yeah, I'm not sure. Maybe that works. I don't know.
But it's up to you to design this and to
backprop through. Yeah, so that's fun. Okay.
So we're going to go to neural networks. This is
exactly what they look like. So you'll be
implementing these, and this is just what happens
when you search on Google Images for
neural networks. This is I think the first
result or something like that. So let's
look at neural networks. And before we dive
into neural networks actually, I'd like
to do it first without all the brain
stuff. So forget that they're neural. Forget
that they have any relation whatsoever
to a brain. They don't, but forget if you
thought that they did, that they do. Let's
just look at score functions. Well
before, we saw that f=Wx is what
we've been working with so far. But now
as I said, we're going to start to make
that f more complex. And so if you wanted
to use a neural network then you're
going to change that equation to this. So
this is a two-layer neural network, and
that's what it looks like, and it's just
a more complex mathematical expression of x.
And so what's happening here is, you
receive your input x, and you
multiply it by a matrix, just like we did before.
Now, what's coming next, what comes next
is a nonlinearity or activation function,
and we're going to go into several choices
that you might make for these. In this
case, I'm using the thresholding at 0 as an
activation function. So basically, we're
doing matrix multiply, we threshold
everything negative to 0, and then we do
one more matrix multiply, and that gives us
our scores. And so if I was to draw this,
say in case of CIFAR-10, with 3072 numbers
going in, those are the pixel values,
and before, we just went one single matrix
multiply to scores. We went right away
to 10 numbers. But now, we get to go
through this intermediate representation
of hidden state. We'll call them hidden layers.
So hidden vector h of hundred numbers, say
or whatever you want your size of the neural
network to be. So this is a hyperparameter,
that's, say, a hundred, and we go through
this intermediate representation. So matrix
multiply gives us hundred
numbers, threshold at zero, and
then one more matrix multiply to get the scores.
And since we have more numbers, we have
more wiggle to do more interesting
things. So a more, one particular example
of something interesting you might want
to, you might think that a neural network
could do, is going back to this
example of interpreting linear
classifiers on CIFAR-10, and we saw that the
car class has this red car that tries to
merge all the modes of different cars
facing in different directions. And so in
this case, one single layer, one single
linear classifier had to go across all
those modes, and we couldn't deal with
for example, cars of different colors. That
wasn't very natural to do. But now we
have hundred numbers in this
intermediate, and so you might imagine
for example, that one of those numbers
could be just picking up on red
car facing forward. It's just classifying,
is there a red car facing
forward. Another one could be red car
facing slightly to the left,
red car facing slightly to the right, and
those elements of h would only become
positive if they find that thing in the image,
otherwise, they stay at zero. And so
another h might look for green cars
or yellow cars or whatever else in
different orientations. So now we can
have a template for all these different
modes. And so these neurons turn on or
off if they find the thing they're looking
for. Car of some specific type, and then
this W2 matrix can sum across all
those little car templates. So now we
have like say twenty card templates of
what cars could look like, and now, to compute
the score of car classifier, there's an
additional matrix multiply, so we have a choice
of doing a weighted sum over them. And so if
anyone of them turn on, then through my
weighted sum, with positive weights
presumably, I would be adding up and
getting a higher score. And so now I can
have this multimodal car classifier
through this additional hidden layer in between
there. So that's a handwavy reason for why
these would do something more interesting.
Was there a question? Yeah.
(Student is asking a question)
So the question is, if h had less than 10 units, would
it be inferior to a linear classifier? I think that's...
that's actually not obvious to me. It's an interesting
question. I think... you could make that work.
I think you could make it work.
Yeah, I think that would actually work. Someone
should try that for extra points in the assignment.
So you'll have a section on the
assignment do something fun or extra
and so you get to come up with whatever you
think is interesting experiment and we'll
give you some bonus points. So that's good
candidate for something you might
want to investigate, whether that works or not.
Any other questions? Go ahead.
(Student is asking a question)
Sorry, I don't think I understood the question.
(Student is asking question)
I see.
So you're really asking about the layout of the
h vector and how it gets allocated over the
the different modes of the dataset
and I don't have a good
answer for that. Since we're going
to train this fully with backpropagation,
I think it's like naive to think that
there will be exact template for, say a
left car facing, red car facing left. You
probably want to find that. You'll find
these kind of like mixes, and weird
things, intermediates, and so on.
So this neural network will come in and it will
optimally find a way to truncate your data
with its linear boundaries
and these weights will all get adjusted
just to make it come out right. So it's
really hard to say. It will all become
tangled up I think. Go ahead.
(Student is asking question)
That's right. So that's the
size of a hidden layer, and it's a hyperparameter.
We get to choose that. So I chose
hundred. Usually that's going to be, usually,
you'll see that with neural networks. We'll go into
this a lot, but usually you want them to
be as big as possible, as it fits in your
computer and so on, so more is better.
We'll go into that. Go ahead.
(Student is asking question)
So you're asking, do we always take max of 0 and h,
and we don't, and I'll get, it's like five slides
away. So I'm going to go into neural networks.
I guess maybe I should preemtively just go
ahead and take questions near the end.
If you wanted this to be a three-layer
neural network by the way, there's a very
simple way in which we just extend
this, right? So we just keep continuing
the same pattern where we have all these
intermediate hidden nodes, and then we
can keep making our network deeper and
deeper, and you can compute more
interesting functions because you're
giving yourself more time to compute
something interesting in a handwavy way.
Now, one other slide I wanted to flash is
that, training a two-layer neural network,
I mean, it's actually quite simple when
it comes down to it. So this is a slide
borrowed from a blog post I found, and
basically it suffices roughly eleven lines of
Python to implement a two layer neural
network, doing binary classification on
what is this, two dimensional data. So you
have a two dimensional data matrix X. You
have, sorry it's three dimensional. And you
have binary labels for y, and then
syn0 syn1 are your weight matrices
weight1 weight2. And so I think they're
called syn for synapse but I'm not sure. And
then this is the optimization loop here
and what you're seeing here, I should
use my pointer for more, what you're
seeing here is we're computing the first
layer activations, but this is using
a sigmoid nonlinearity not a max of 0 and X.
And we'll go into a bit of what
these nonlinearities might be. So sigmoid is
one form. It's computing the first layer,
and then it's computing second layer, and then
it's computing here right away the backward
pass. So this is the l2_delta. It's the gradient
on l2, the gradient on l1, and the
gradient, and this is an update here.
So right away he's doing an update at
the same time as during the final piece
of backprop here where he formulating the
gradient on the W, and right away he's
adding to gradient here. And so really
eleven lines suffice to train a
neural network to do binary
classification. The reason that this loss
might look slightly different from what
you've seen right now, is that this is a
logistic regression loss. So you saw a
generalization of it which is a softmax
classifier into multiple dimensions. But
this is basically a logistic loss being
updated here and you can go through this
in more detail by yourself. But the
logistic regression loss look slightly
different and that's being, that's inside
there. But otherwise, yes, so this is not too
crazy of a computation, and very few
lines of code suffice to actually train
these networks. Everything else is fluff.
How do you make it efficient, how do
you... there's a cross-validation pipeline
that you need to have and all this stuff
that goes on top to actually give these
large code bases, but the kernel of it is
quite simple. We compute these layers, do
forward pass, we do backward pass, we do an
update, we keep iterating this over and over again.
Go ahead.
(Student is asking a question)
The random function is creating
your first initial random
weights, so you need to start somewhere
so you generate a random W.
Okay. Now I wanted to mention that you'll also
be training a two-layer neural network
in this class, so you'll be doing
something very similar to this but
you're not using logistic regression and
you might have different activation
functions. But again, just my advice to
you when you implement this is, stage
your computation into these intermediate
results, and then do proper
backpropagation into every intermediate
result. So you might have, you compute
your... Let's see. You compute, you receive these
weight matrices and also the biases. I don't
believe you have biases actually in your SVM and in
your softmax, but here you'll have biases. So
take your weight matrices in the biases,
compute the first hidden layer, compute your scores,
compute your loss, and then do backward
pass. So backprop into scores, then
backprop into the weights at the second
layer, and backprop into this h1 vector,
and then through h1, backprop into the first
weight matrices and the first biases. Okay, so do
proper backpropagation here. Otherwise, if
you try to right away, just say, what
is dW1, what is the gradient on W1. If you
just try to make it a single expression
for it, it will be way too large and you'll have
headaches. So do it through a series of
steps and back-propagation.
That's just a hint.
Okay. So now I'd like to, so that was the
presentation of neural networks without
all the brain stuff and it looks fairly
simple. So now we're going to make it
slightly more insane by folding in all
kinds of like motivations, mostly
historical about like how this came
about that it's related to brain at all.
And so, we have neural networks and we
have neurons inside these neural
networks. So this is what neurons look like.
This is just what happens when you search on
image search 'neurons', so there you go. Now
your actual biological neurons don't
look like this. Unfortunately, they look
more like that. And so a neuron,
just very briefly, just to give you an
idea about where this is all coming from
you have the cell body or a soma as people like
to call it, and it's got all these dendrites
that are connected to other neurons. So
there's a cluster of other neurons and
cell bodies over here. And dendrites are
really, these appendages that listen to
them. So this is your inputs to a neuron,
and then it's got a single axon that
comes out of the neuron that carries the
output of the computation that this neurons performs.
So usually, usually you have this
neuron, receives inputs. If many of them
align, then this cell, this neuron can
choose to spike. It says an activation
potential down the axon and then this
actually like diverges out to
connect to dendrites of other neurons that
are downstream. So there are other
neurons here and their dendrites
connect to the axons of these guys.
So basically, just neurons connected through
these synapses in between and we had these
dendrites that are the input to a neuron and
this axon that actually carries the
output of a neuron. And so basically, you
can come up with a very crude model of a
neuron, and it will look something like this.
We have an axon, so this is the cell body
here of a neuron. And just imagine an
axon coming from a different neuron,
somewhere in the network, and this neuron is
connected to that neuron through this
synapse. And every one of these synapses
has a weight associated with it
of how much this neuron likes that
neuron basically. And so axon carries
this x. It interacts in the synapse and
they multiply in this crude model. So you
get w0x0 flowing to the soma.
And then that happens for many neurons
so you have lots of
inputs of w times x flowing in. And the
cell body here, it just performs a sum, offset by
a bias, and then if an activation function
is met here, so it passes through an
activation function to actually compute
the output of this axon. Now in
biological models, historically people
liked to use the sigmoid nonlinearity to
actually use for the activation function.
The reason for that is because
you get a number between 0 and 1, and
you can interpret that as the rate at
which this neuron is firing for that
particular input. So it's a rate between
0 and 1 that's going through the
activation function. So if this neuron has
seen something it likes, in the neurons
that connected to it, it will start to
spike a lot, and the rate is described by
f of the input. Okay, so that's the crude
model of the neuron. If I wanted to implement it
it would look something like this. So a
neuron_tick function forward pass, it receives
some inputs. This is a vector and we form
a sum at the cell body, so just a linear sum.
And we put, we compute the firing rate as a sigmoid
of the cell body sum and return the firing
rate. And then this can plug into
different neurons, right? So you can
imagine, you can actually see that this
looks very similar to a linear
classifier, right? We're forming a linear sum here,
a weighted sum, and we're passing that through
nonlinearity. So every single neuron in
this model is really like a small linear
classifier, but these linear classifiers plug into
each other, and they can work together to
do interesting things. Now one note to make
about neurons is that they're very, they're
not like biological neurons. Biological
neurons are super complex, so if you go
around and you start saying that neural
networks work like brain, people are
starting to frown. People will start to frown
at you and that's because neurons are
complex, dynamical systems. There are many
different types of neurons. They function
differently. These dendrites, they
can perform lots of interesting
computation. A good review article is
Dendritic Computation, which I really
enjoyed. These synapses are complex
dynamical systems. They're not just a
single weight. And we're not really sure
if the brain uses rate code to
communicate, so very crude mathematical
model and don't push his analogy too much.
But it's good for, kind of like, media articles,
so I suppose that's why this keeps
coming up again and again as we
explained that this works like your brain.
But I'm not going to go too deep into
this. To go back to a question that was
asked before, there's an entire set of
nonlinearities that we can choose from.
So historically, sigmoid has been used
quite a bit, and we're going to go into
much more detail over what these
nonlinearities are, what are their
tradeoffs, and why you might want to use
one or the other, but for now, I'd just like to
flash them and mention that there are many things to
choose from.
Historically people use to signmoid and tanh.
As of 2012, ReLU became quite popular.
It makes your networks converge quite a bit
faster, so right now, if you wanted a
default choice for nonlinearity, use ReLU.
That's the current default recommendation.
And then there's a few, kind of a hipster
activation functions here. And so Leaky ReLUs
were proposed a few years ago. Maxout is
interesting. And very recently ELU.
And so you can come up with different
activation functions and you can
describe why these might work better or
not. And so this is an active area of
research. It's trying to come up with these
activation functions that perform, that
have better properties in one way or
another. So we're going to go into this with much
more detail soon in the class. But for
now, we have these neurons, we have a
choice of activation function, and then
we arrange these neurons into neural
networks, right? So we just connect them
together so they can talk to each other.
And so here is an example of a
2-layer neural net or 3-layer neural net. When
you want to count the number of layers and the
neural net, you count the number of
layers that have weights. So here, the
input layer does not count as a layer,
because there's no... These neurons are just
single values. They don't actually do any
computation. So we have two layers here
that have weights. So it's a 2-layer net. And
we call these layers fully connected
layers, and so, remember that I shown you that a
single neuron computes this little
weighted sum, and then passed that through
nonlinearity. In a neural network, the
reason we arrange these into layers is
because arranging them into layers allows
us to perform the computation much more
efficiently. So instead of having an
amorphous blob of neurons and every one
of them has to be computed independently,
having them in layers allows us to use
vectorized operations. And so we can
compute an entire set of
neurons in a single hidden layer as just
at a single times a matrix multiply. And
that's why we arrange them in these
layers, where neurons inside a layer can be
evaluated completely in parallel, and they
all see the same input. So it's a
computational trick to arrange them in
layers. So this is a 3-layer neural net
and this is how you would compute it.
Just a bunch of matrix multiplies
followed by activation function.
So now I'd
like to show you a demo of how these
neural networks work. So this is JavaScript demo
that I'll show you in a bit. But
basically, this is an example of a
two-layer neural network classifying a,
doing a binary classification task. So we have two
classes, red and green. And so we have these
points in two dimensions, and I'm drawing
the decision boundaries by the neural
network. And so what you can see is, when
I train a neural network on this data,
the more hidden neurons I have in my
hidden layer, the more wiggle your neural
network has, right? The more it can compute
crazy functions. And just to show you effect
also of regularization strength. So this is the
regularization of how much you penalize
large Ws. So you can see that when you insist
that your Ws are very small, you end up with
a very smooth functions, so they don't
have as much variance. So these neural
networks, there's not as much wiggle
that they can give you, and then as you
decrease the regularization, these neural
networks can do more and more complex
tasks, so they can kind of get in and get
these little squeezed out points to cover
them in a training data. So let me show
you what this looks like
during training. Okay.
So there're some stuff to explain here.
Let me first actually... So you can play with
this because it's all in JavaScript.
Okay. All right. So what we're doing here is we have
six neurons, and this is a binary
classification dataset with circle
data. And so we have a little cluster of
green dots separated by red dots. And we're
training a neural network to classify
this dataset. So if I restart the neural
network, it's just, starts off with a
random W, and then it converges the
decision boundary to actually classify
the data. What I'm showing on the right, which is the
cool part, this visualization, is one interpretation of
the neural network here, is what I'm
taking this grid here and I'm
showing how this space gets warped by
the neural network. So you can interpret
what the neural network is doing is it's
using its hidden layer to transform your
input data in such a way that the second
hidden layer can come in with a linear
classifier and classify your data. So
here, you see that the neural network
arranges your space. It warps it such
that the second layer, which is really a
linear classifier on top of the first
layer, can put a plane through it, okay?
So it's warping the space so that you
can put a plane through it and
separate out the points. So let's look at
this again. So you can roughly see what
how this gets warped so that you can
linearly classify the data. This is
something that people sometimes also
referred to as kernel trick. It's
changing your data representation to a
space where it's linearly separable. Okay.
Now, here's a question. If we'd like to
separate, so right now we have six
neurons here in the intermediate layer,
and it allows us to separate out these
data points. So you can see actually those six
neurons roughly. You can see these lines
here, like they're kind of like these
functions of one of these neurons. So
here's a question for you, What is the
minimum number of neurons for which this
dataset is separable with a neural
network? If I want the neural network
to correctly classify this, how many neurons do
I need in the hidden layer as a minimum?
Four? I heard some threes, some fours.
Binary search.
So intuitively, the way this
would work is, let's see four.
So what happens with four is, there is one
neuron here that went from this way to
that way, this way to that way, this way
to that way. There's four neurons that
are cutting up this plane. And then
there's an additional layer that's doing a
weighted sum. So in fact, the lowest
number here would be three, which
would work. So with three neurons... So
one plane, second plane, third plane. So
three linear functions with a nonlinearity,
and then you can basically with three
lines, you can carve out the space so
that the second layer can just combine
them when their numbers are 1 and not 0.
(Student is asking question)
At two? Certainly. So at two, this will break
because two lines are not enough. I
suppose this works... Not going to look very
good here. So with two, basically it will find
the optimal way of just using these two
lines. They're kind of creating this
tunnel and that's the best you can do. Okay?
(Student is asking question)
The curve, I think... Which nonlinearity am I using?
tanh? Yeah, I'm not sure exactly how that works out.
If I was using ReLU, I think it would be much,
so ReLU is the... Let me change to ReLU, and I
think you'd see sharp boundaries. Yeah.
Yes, this is three. You can do four. So let's do...
(Student is asking question)
Yeah, that's because, it's
because in some of these parts
there's more than one of those ReLUs
are active, and so you end up with...
There are really three lines. I think like one, two,
three, but then in some of the corners two ReLU
neurons are active and so these
weights will add up. It's kind of funky. You
have to think about a bit. But okay. So let's
look at, say, twenty here. So I changed to twenty
so we have lots of space there, and let's
look at different datasets like say spiral.
So you can see how this thing just, as I'm
doing this update, it  will just go in there
and figure that out. Very simple dataset
is not... Spiral. Circle, and then random...
so random data, and so you could, kind
of goes in there, like covers up the green
ones and the red ones. And yeah. And with
fewer, say like five... I'm going to break this
now. I'm not going to... Okay. So with five... Yes.
So this will start working worse and worse
because you don't have enough capacity
to separate out this data. So you can
play with this in your free time.
Okay. And so as a summary,
we arrange these neurons in neural
networks into fully connected layers.
We've looked at backprop and how this gets
chained in computational graphs. And they're
not really neural. And as we'll see soon,
the bigger the better, and we'll go into
that a lot. I want to take questions before I end.
Just sorry. Were there any questions? Go ahead.
(Student is asking question)
We have two more minutes. Sorry.
Yes, thank you.
So is it always better to have more neurons
in your neural network? The answer to
that is yes. More is always better. It's
usually computational constraint, so more will
always work better, but then you have to
be careful to regularize it properly. So
the correct way to constrain your neural
network to not overfit your data is not by
making the network smaller.
The correct way to do it is to increase the
regularization. So you always want to use
as large a network as you want, but then
you have to make sure to properly
regularize it. But most of the time
because of computational reasons, you have finite
amount of time, you don't want to wait forever to
train your networks. You'll use smaller
ones for practical reasons. Question?
(Student is asking question)
Do you regularize each layer equally.
Usually you do, as a simplification.
Yeah. Most of the, often when you see
networks get trained in practice, they will
be regularized the same way throughout.
But you don't have to necessarily. Go ahead.
(Student is asking question)
Is there any value to using second derivatives using
hashing in optimizing neural networks? There is value
sometimes when your data sets are small.
You can use things like L-BFGS which I
didn't go into too much, and that's a
second order method, but usually the datasets
are really large and that's when
L-BFGS doesn't work very well.
So when you millions of data points, you can't do
L-BFGS for various reasons. Yeah. And L-BFGS is
not very good with minibatch. You always
have to do full batch by default. Question.
(Student is asking question)
So what is the tradeoff between depth and
size roughly, like how do you allocate?
Not a good answer for that unfortunately.
So you want, depth is good, but maybe after
like ten layers maybe, if you have simple dataet
it's not really adding too much. We have
one more minute so I can still take some
questions. You had a question for a while.
(Student is asking question)
Yeah, so the tradeoff between
where do I allocate my
capacity, do I want us to be deeper or do
I want it to be wider, not a very good
answer to that.
(Student is asking question)
Yes, usually, especially with
images, we find that more layers are
critical. But sometimes when you have
simple datasets like 2D or some
other things like depth is not as
critical, and so it's kind of slightly
data dependent. We had a question over there.
(Student is asking question)
Different activation functions for different layers,
does that help? Usually it's not done. Usually we
just kind of pick one and go with it.
So say, for ConvNets for example, we'll see that
most of them are trained just with ReLUs.
And so you just use that throughout and
there's no real benefit to switch
them around. People don't play with that
too much, but in principle, there's
nothing preventing you. So it is 4:20,
so we're going to end here, but we'll see
lots of more neural networks, so a lot of
these questions, we'll go through them.